<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC5905 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2827 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2434 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2434.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4786 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4786.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7094 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7094.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-reilly-ntp-bcp-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Network Time Protocol BCP">Network Time Protocol Best
    Current Practices</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Denis Reilly" initials="D." surname="Reilly">
      <organization>Spectracom Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1565 Jefferson Road, Suite 460</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Rochester, NY</city>

          <region/>

          <code>14623</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>denis.reilly@spectracom.orolia.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- Leave Harlan as a ghost contributor for the moment  -->

    <!--
    <author fullname="Harlan Stenn" initials="H."
            surname="Stenn">
      <organization>Network Time Foundation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 918</street>

          <city>Talent, OR</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>97540</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>stenn@nwtime.org</email>

      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <!-- Dieter's Info -->

    <!--
    <author fullname="Dieter Sibold" initials="D." surname="Sibold">
      <organization abbrev="PTB">Physikalisch-Technische
      Bundesanstalt</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bundesallee 100</street>

          <city>Braunschweig</city>

          <code>D-38116</code>

          <region/>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49-(0)531-592-8420</phone>

        <facsimile>+49-531-592-698420</facsimile>

        <email>dieter.sibold@ptb.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <!-- Leave Sam as a ghost contributor for the moment  -->

    <!--    <author fullname="Samuel Weiler" initials="H."
            surname="Weiler">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>US</country>
	  </postal>
	<phone></phone>
        <email>weiler+ietf@watson.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <date month="March" year="2016"/>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>NTP</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>NTP Version 4 (NTPv4) has been widely used since its publication as
      <xref target="RFC5905">RFC 5905</xref>. This documentation is a
      collection of Best Practices from across the NTP community.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>NTP Version 4 (NTPv4) has been widely used since its publication as
      <xref target="RFC5905">RFC 5905</xref>. This documentation is a
      collection of Best Practices from across the NTP community.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Keeping NTP up to date">
      <t>No software (not even NTP) is perfect. Bugs can be present in any
      software. As software is widely deployed, users find more bugs. And even
      if software is thoroughly tested and "all" the bugs are wrung out, users
      continuously find new ways to use software that their authors did not
      conceive of, which can uncover more bugs. Thousands of individual bugs
      have been found and fixed in the NTP Project's reference implementation
      since the first NTPv4 release in 1997.</t>

      <t>In addition, there are always new ideas about security on the
      Internet, and an application which is secure today could be insecure
      tomorrow once an unknown bug (or a known behavior) is exploited in the
      right way. Many security mechanisms rely on time, either directly or
      indirectly, as part of their operation. If an attacker can spoof the
      time, they may be able to bypass or neutralize other security elements.
      It will certainly disrupt the ability to reconcile logfile entries on
      the affected box with events on other systems.</t>

      <t>In general, the best way to protect yourself and your networks
      against these bugs and security threats is to make sure that you keep
      your NTP implementation up-to-date. There are multiple versions of the
      NTP protocol in use and multiple implementations and versions of NTP
      software also in use, on many different platforms. It is advised that
      NTP users actively monitor wherever they get their software to find out
      if their versions are vulnerable to any known attacks, when updates are
      available, and deploy updates containing security fixes as soon as
      practical.</t>

      <t>The reference implementation of NTP Version 4 from Network Time
      Foundation (NTF) continues to be actively maintained and developed by
      NTF's NTP Project, with help from volunteers and NTF's supporters. The
      NTP software can be downloaded from http://www.ntp.org/downloads.html
      and also from https://github.com/ntp-project/ntp .</t>
    </section>

    <section title="General Network Security Best Practices">
      <t>NTP deployments are only as secure as the networks they are running
      over.</t>

      <section anchor="bcp38" title="BCP 38">
        <t>Many network attacks rely on modifying the IP source address of a
        packet to point to a different IP address than the computer which
        originated it. This modification/abuse vector has been known for quite
        some time, and <xref target="RFC2827">BCP 38</xref> was approved in
        2000 to address this. This document <!-- HMS: which document, BCP38 or this one? -->
        calls for filtering outgoing and incoming traffic to make sure that
        the source and destination IP addresses are consistent with the
        expected flow of traffic on each network interface. It's recommended
        that all networks (and ISP's of any size) implement this. If a machine
        on your network is sending out packets claiming to be from an address
        that is not on your network, this could be the first indication that
        you have a machine that has been cracked, and is being used abusively.
        If packets are arriving on an external interface with a source address
        that should only be seen on an internal network, that's a strong
        indication that an attacker is trying to inject spoofed packets into
        your network. More information is available at http://www.bcp38.info
        .</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="NTP Configuration Best Practices">
      <t>NTP can be made more secure by making a few simple changes to the
      ntp.conf file.</t>

      <!-- See https://support.ntp.org/bin/view/Support/ConfiguringNTP -->

      <section title="Use enough time sources">
        <t>NTP takes the available sources of time and submits their timing
        data to intersection and clustering algorithms, looking for the best
        idea of the correct time. If there is only 1 source of time, the
        answer is obvious. It may not be a good source of time, but it's the
        only one. If there are 2 sources of time and they agree well enough,
        that's good. But if they don't, then ntpd has no way to know which
        source to believe. This gets easier if there are 3 sources of time.
        But if one of those 3 sources becomes unreachable or unusable, we're
        back to only having 2 time sources. 4 sources of time is another
        interesting choice, assuming things go well. If one of these sources
        develops a problem there are still 3 others. Seems good. Until the
        leap-second we had in June of 2015, where several operators decided to
        offer "leap smeared" time service, and people discovered that two of
        their upstream servers were offering UTC time while the other two were
        offering "leap smeared" time. The net effect of this was there was no
        clear majority to follow.</t>

        <t>Starting with ntp-4.2.6, the 'pool' directive will spin up "enough"
        associations to provide robust time service, and will disconnect poor
        servers and add in new servers as-needed.</t>

        <t>Monitor your ntpd instances. If your times sources do not generally
        agree, find out why and either correct the problems or stop using
        defective servers. See <xref target="Monitoring"/> for more
        information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use a diversity of Reference Clocks">
        <t>If you are using reference clocks, are they all from the same
        vendor? Are they using the same base chipset, regardless of whether or
        not the finished products are from different vendors? Are they all
        running the same version of firmware? A systemic problem with time
        from any satellite navigation service is possible and has happened.
        Sunspot activity can render satellite or radio-based time sources
        unusable. A chipset problem can happen. There may be a bug in the
        vendor's firmware.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="mode67" title="Mode 6 and 7">
        <t>NTP Mode 6 (ntpq) and Mode 7 (ntpdc) packets are designed to permit
        monitoring and optional authenticated control of ntpd and its
        configuration. Used properly, these facilities provide vital debugging
        and performance information and control. Used improperly, these
        facilities can be an abuse vector.</t>

        <t>Mode 7 queries have been disabled by default since 4.2.7p230,
        released on 2011/11/01. Unless you have a good reason for using ntpdc,
        do not enable Mode 7.</t>

        <t>The ability to use Mode 6 beyond its basic monitoring capabilities
        can be limited to authenticated sessions that provide a 'controlkey',
        and similarly, if Mode 7 has been explicitly enabled its use for more
        than masic monitoring can be limited to authenticated sessions that
        provide a 'requestkey'.</t>

        <t>Older versions of the reference implementation of NTP could be
        abused to participate in high-bandwidth DDoS attacks. Starting with
        ntp-4.2.7p26, released in April of 2010, ntpd requires the use of a
        nonce before replying with potentially large response packets. <!-- Cite relevant CVEs, NTP bug reports, and release notes? --></t>

        <t>As mentioned above, there are two general ways to use Mode 6 and
        Mode 7 requests. One way is to query ntpd for information, and this
        mode can be disabled with:</t>

        <t>restrict ... noquery</t>

        <t>The second way to use Mode 6 and Mode 7 requests is to modify
        ntpd's behavior. Modification of ntpd ordinarily requires an
        authenticated session. By default, if no authentication keys have been
        specified no modifications can be made. For additional protection, the
        ability to perform these modifications can be controlled with:</t>

        <t>restrict ... nomodify</t>

        <!-- Should we talk about notrap ? -->

        <!-- the following ntp.conf fragment examples are version-specific.
	     Which versions should we show examples for? -->

        <t>Users can prevent their NTP servers from participating by adding
        the following to their ntp.conf file:</t>

        <t>restrict default -4 nomodify notrap nopeer noquery</t>

        <t>restrict default -6 nomodify notrap nopeer noquery</t>

        <t>restrict source nomodify notrap noquery # nopeer is OK if you don't
        use the 'pool' directive</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Monitoring" title="Monitoring">
        <t>The reference implementation of NTP allows remote monitoring. The
        access to this service is controlled by the restrict statement in
        NTP's configuration file (ntp.conf). The syntax reads:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[restrict address mask address_mask nomodify]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Monitor your ntpd instances so machines that are "out of sync" can
        be quickly identified. Monitor your system logs for messages from ntpd
        so abuse attempts can be quickly identified.</t>

        <t>If your system starts getting unexpected time replies from its time
        servers, that can be an indication that the IP address of your server
        is being forged in requests to that time server, and these abusers are
        trying to convince your time servers to stop serving time to you.</t>

        <!-- Cite CVEs, BU paper, bug reports? -->

        <t>If your system is a broadcast client and your syslog shows that you
        are receiving "early" time messages from your server, that is an
        indication that somebody may be forging packets from a broadcast
        server.</t>

        <!-- Cite CVEs, BU paper, bug reports? -->

        <t>If your syslog shows messages that indicate you are receiving
        timestamps that are earlier than the current system time, then either
        your system clock is unusually fast or somebody is trying to launch a
        replay attack against your server.</t>

        <!-- Cite CVEs, BU
	paper, bug reports? -->

        <t>If you are using broadcast mode and have ntp-4.2.8p6 or later, use
        the 4th field of the ntp.keys file to identify the IPs of machines
        that are allowed to serve time to the group.</t>

        <!-- Cite
	CVEs, BU paper, bug reports? -->

      </section>

      <section title="Security">
        <t>In the standard configuration NTP packets are exchanged unprotected
        between client and server. An adversary that is able to become a
        Man-In-The-Middle is therefore able to drop, replay or modify the
        content of the NTP packet, which leads to degradation of the time
        synchronization or the transmission of false time information. A
        profound threat analysis for time synchronization protocols are given
        in <xref target="RFC7384">RFC 7384</xref>. NTP provides two security
        measures to protect authenticity and integrity of the NTP packets.
        Both measures protect the NTP packet by means of a Message
        Authentication Code (MAC). Neither of them encrypts the NTP's payload,
        because it is not considered to be confidential.</t>

        <section title="Pre-Shared Key Approach">
          <t>This approach applies a symmetric key for the calculation of the
          MAC, which protects authenticity and integrity of the exchanged
          packets for a association. NTP does not provide a mechanism for the
          exchange of the keys between the associated nodes. Therefore, for
          each association, keys have to be exchanged securely by external
          means. It is recommended that each association is protected by an
          own unique key. NTP does not provide a mechanism to automatically
          refresh the applied keys. It is therefore recommended that the
          participants periodically agree on a refresh key. The calculation of
          the MAC may always be based on an MD5 hash. If the NTP daemon is
          built against an OpenSSL library, NTP can also base the calculation
          of the MAC upon the SHA-1 or any other digest algorithm supported by
          each side's OpenSSL library.</t>

          <t>To use this approach the communication partners have to exchange
          the key, which consists of a keyid with a value between 1 and 65534,
          inclusive, and a label which indicates the chosen digest algorithm.
          Each communication partner adds this information to their key file
          in the form:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[keyid label key]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The key file contains the key in clear text. Therefore it should
          only be readable by the NTP process. Different keys are added line
          by line to the key file.</t>

          <t>A NTP client establishes a protected association by appending the
          option "key keyid" to the server statement in the NTP configuration
          file:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[server address key keyid]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>Note that the NTP process has to trust the applied key. An NTP
          process explicitly has to add each key it want to trust to a list of
          trusted keys by the "trustedkey" statement in the NTP configuration
          file.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[trustedkey keyid_1 keyid_2 ... keyid_n]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t/>
        </section>

        <section title="Autokey">
          <t>Autokey was designed in 2003 to provide a means for clients to
          authenticate servers. By 2011, security researchers had identified
          computational areas in the Autokey protocol that, while secure at
          the time of its original design, were no longer secure. Work was
          begun on an enhanced replacement for Autokey, which was called
          Network Time Security.
          https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-ntp-network-time-security-00
          was published in the summer of 2013. As of February 2016, this
          effort was at draft #13, and about to begin 'final call'. The first
          unicast implementation of NTS was started in the summer of 2015 and
          is expected to be released in the summer of 2016.</t>

          <t>We recommend that Autokey NOT BE USED. Know that as of the fall
          of 2011, a common(?) laptop computer could crack the security cookie
          used in the Autokey protocol in 30 minutes' time. If you must use
          Autokey, know that your session keys should be set to expire in
          under 30 minutes' time. If you have reason to believe your
          autokey-protected associations will be attacked, you should read
          https://lists.ntp.org/pipermail/ntpwg/2011-August/001714.html and
          decide what resources your attackers might be using, and adjust the
          session key expiration time accordingly.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="External Security Means">
          <t>TBD</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Using Pool Servers">
        <t>It only takes a small amount of bandwidth and system resources to
        synchronize one NTP client, but NTP servers that can service tens of
        thousands of clients take more resources to run. Users who want to
        synchronize their computers should only synchronize to servers that
        they have permission to use.</t>

        <t>The NTP pool project is a collection of volunteers who have donated
        their computing and bandwidth resources to provide time on the
        Internet for free. The time is generally of good quality, but comes
        with no guarantee whatsoever. If you are interested in using the pool,
        please review their instructions at
        http://www.pool.ntp.org/en/use.html .</t>

        <t>If you want to synchronize many computers using the pool, consider
        running your own NTP servers, synchronizing them to the pool, and
        synchronizing your clients to your in-house NTP servers. This reduces
        the load on the pool.</t>

        <t>Set up or sponsor one or more pool servers.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Starting, Cold-Starting, and Re-Starting NTP">
        <t>Only use -g on cold-start. Other things TBD.</t>

        <t>Editor's Note: I think I'd like to expand this a bit to cover how
        to deal with NTP stopping, when to restart it, and under what
        circumstances to not restart it!</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Leap Second Handling">
        <t>The UTC timescale is kept in sync with the rotation of the earth 
        through the use of leap seconds. More details are available {here}. 
        </t>

        <t>NTP time is based on the UTC timescale, and the protocol has the 
        capability to broadcast leap second information. GPS (and most other 
        GNSS systems) broadcast leap second information as part of the satellite 
        data, so if you have a Stratum-1 server synced to GPS (or you are synced 
        to a lower stratum server that is ultimately synced to GPS), you will get 
        advance notification of impending leap seconds automatically.</t>

        <t>NIST maintains a leap second list for NTP users who are not receiving 
        leap second information through an automatic source.  
        [ftp://tycho.usno.navy.mil/pub/ntp/leap-seconds.list] 
        After fetching the leap seconds file onto the server, add this line to 
        ntpd.conf to apply the file:</t>

        <t>leapfile "/path/to your/leap-file"</t>

        <t>You will need to restart to apply the changes.</t>

        <section title="Leap Smearing">
          <t>Some NTP installations may instead make use of a technique called 
          "Leap Smearing".  With this method, instead of introducing an extra 
          second (or eliminating a second), NTP time will be slewed in small 
          increments over a comparably large window of time around the leap 
          second event. The amount of the slew should be small enough that 
          clients will follow the smeared time without objecting. During the 
          adjustment window, the NTP server's time may be offset from UTC by as 
          much as .5 seconds.  This is done to enable software that doesn't deal
          with minutes that have more or less than 60 seconds to function 
          correctly, at the expense of fidelity to UTC during the smear window.</t> 
          <!--find a reference, possibly Google or Meinberg -->

          <t>When using NTP servers from across the Internet, users should be 
          aware that some servers may smear the leap second, while others may 
          jump (while a third, hopefully smaller, group may ignore it 
          altogether). Users are advised to be aware of impending leap seconds 
          and how the servers they are using deal with them. </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="NTP in Embedded Devices">
      <t>Readers of this BCP already understand how important accurate time is
      for network computing. And as computing becomes more ubiquitous, there
      will be many small "Internet of Things" devices that require accurate
      time. These embedded devices may not have a traditional user interface,
      but if they connect to the Internet they will be subject to the same
      security threats as traditional deployments.</t>

      <section title="Updating Embedded Devices">
        <t>Vendors of embedded devices have a special responsibility to pay
        attention to the current state of NTP bugs and security issues,
        because their customers usually don't have the ability to update their
        NTP implementation on their own. Those devices may have a single
        firmware upgrade, provided by the manufacturer, that updates all
        capabilities at once. This means that the vendor essentially assumes
        the responsibility of making sure their devices have the latest NTP
        updates applied.</t>

        <t>This should also include the ability to update the NTP server
        address.</t>

        <t>(Note: do we find specific historical instances of devices behaving
        badly and cite them here?)</t>
      </section>

      <section title="KISS Packets">
        <t>The "Kiss-o'-Death" packet is a rate limiting mechanism where a
        server can tell a misbehaving client to "back off" its query rate. It
        is important for all NTP devices to respect these packets and back off
        when asked to do so by a server. It is even more important for an
        embedded device, which may not have exposed a control interface for
        NTP.</t>

        <!-- mixed blessing - can be used as a DoS vector.  Some
	poorly-implemented clients will actually *increase* the rate at
	which they poll a server if they are sent a KoD packet. -->
      </section>

      <section title="Server configuration">
        <t>Vendors of embedded devices that need time synchronization should
        also carefully consider where they get their time from. There are
        several public-facing NTP servers available, but they may not be
        prepared to service requests from thousands of new devices on the
        Internet.</t>

        <t>Vendors are encouraged to invest resources into providing their own
        time servers for their devices.</t>

        <section title="Get a vendor subdomain for pool.ntp.org">
          <t>The NTP Pool Project offers a program where vendors can obtain
          their own subdomain that is part of the NTP Pool. This offers
          vendors the ability to safely make use of the time distributed by
          the Pool for their devices. Vendors are encouraged to support the
          pool if they participate. For more information, visit
          http://www.pool.ntp.org/en/vendors.html .</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="NTP Deployment Examples">
      <t>A few examples of interesting NTP Deployments</t>

      <!-- These should likely be version-specific. -->

      <section title="Client-Only configuration">
        <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Server-Only Configuration">
        <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Anycast">
        <t>Anycast is described in <xref target="RFC4786">BCP 126</xref>.
        (Also see <xref target="RFC7094">RFC 7094</xref>). With anycast, a
        single IP address is assigned to multiple interfaces, and routers
        direct packets to the closest active interface.</t>

        <t>Anycast is often used for Internet services at known IP addresses,
        such as DNS. Anycast can also be used in large organizations to
        simplify configuration of a large number of NTP clients. Each client
        can be configured to the same IP address, and a pool of anycast
        servers can be deployed to service those requests. New servers can be
        added to or taken from the pool, and other than a temporary loss of
        service while a server is taken down, these additions can be
        transparent to the clients.</t>

        <t>If clients are connected to an NTP server via anycast, the client
        does not know which particular server they are connected to. And as
        anycast servers may arbitrarily enter and leave the network, the
        server a particular client is connected to may change, which can cause
        temporary problems on the client. It is recommended that anycast is
        avoided in environments where precision synchronization is
        required.</t>

        <t>A client also may not have any way to diagnose if an anycast server
        is not functioning properly. It is recommended that any anycast NTP
        implementation include multiple interfaces with at least one Unicast
        address. These Unicast addresses should be monitored (perhaps in a
        peering arrangement) so that if one server's reference goes bad, it
        can use the other servers to validate the correct time.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author wishes to acknowledge the contributions of Harlan Stenn,
      Sue Graves, Samuel Weiler, Dieter Sibold, and Karen O'Donoghue.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>

      <!--This entire document is one big Security Consideration. Do we 
          just reference the appropriate sections? -->

      <!-- SW: We need to also say that 1) NTP security
	    considerations, in general, are discussed in RFC XXX; and
	    2) the suggestions in this doc do not have security
	    impacts (to the extent that is true).  -->
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      &RFC2119;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml"?-->

      &RFC5905;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml"?-->

      &RFC2827;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml"?-->

      &RFC4786;

      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml"?-->

      &RFC7094;

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7384'?>
    </references>

    <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

    <!-- SW: Except that we're not really using these...

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3552;

      &I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis;
 
    </references> 
     -->

    <!--
    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>
-->

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2015-09-18  DPR Initial Submission   
                                                                                        -->
  </back>
</rfc>
